Okay, welcome back, and the next section that we're going to cover is chronic inflammation.
This is just in the sequence of inflammation that we've been covering within Chapter 2.
This particular section reminds us that it starts by discussing the fact that
chronic inflammation is characterized by lymphocytes and plasma cells in tissue.
Remember that I told you that basically the idea behind inflammation is that
inflammation is getting what's present within the blood vessel into the tissue space,
and that within the blood vessel can be lymphocytes and are neutrophils.
And when you bring neutrophils out into the tissue space, that's called acute inflammation.
And when you call lymphocytes into the tissue space, that's called chronic inflammation.
And those lymphocytes can also become plasma cells.
And so the chronic inflammatory state is basically characterized by the presence of
lymphocytes and plasma cells in tissue.
Now, it's important to remember that this is a delayed response.
It doesn't occur immediately.
It takes some time to generate, usually a couple days.
But it's more specific than the innate immune system, more specific than the neutrophils.
And it is an example of adaptive immunity.
And we've already talked about adaptive immunity at the very beginning of this chapter.
And so I won't dwell on that here.
Here's an image just reminding you of the characteristic cells that are present in chronic inflammation.
And so you can see that all of these cells are mononuclear.
They don't have that multilobated nuclear look of a neutrophil.
And we can see particularly that, for example, within here is a lymphocyte, and here is a plasma cell.
Plasma cells are characterized by nuclei that are off to the edge of the cell with a little bit of this sort of glossy clearing next to the nucleus.
And you can kind of make that out over here.
I'm going to erase it so you can now see it.
But this is the plasma cell with a nucleus pushed off to the side and this little area of sort of glassy, shiny cytoplasm, which is characteristic of the plasma cell.
And you can see adjacent to it here is a lymphocyte.
And so these are the hallmark cells of chronic inflammation.
Now, chronic inflammation is going to arise in the context of certain stimuli, the same way that acute inflammation arose in the context of certain stimuli.
And the most common stimulus for chronic inflammation is persistent infection.
This really is the most common stimulus.
Other things that can lead to chronic inflammation include viruses, microbacteria, parasites, and fungi.
These all require chronic inflammation in order to be resolved.
Another example would be autoimmune disease.
So patients with autoimmune disease get abnormal, chronic inflammation.
Foreign material can result in chronic inflammation.
And some cancers.
One of the major mechanisms by which cancers are attacked and destroyed is via a chronic inflammatory state.
And we'll talk more about cancers and inflammation when we discuss your chapter on neoplasia.
Remember that when you think about lymphocytes, lymphocytes can be divided into T cells and B cells.
And so I want to just give you a little bit of an immunology review here so that our discussions will be made so that it will be easier to discuss some of the diseases that I want to talk about.
So let's start with T cells.
T cells are made in the bone marrow.
They're born as progenitor T cells.
And after they're born as progenitor T cells, they go to the thymus to receive education.
Remember that it's in the thymus that they basically go to college.
And in the thymus, they learn how to undergo T cell rearrangement.
So their T cell receptor rearrangement, their TCR or T cell receptor undergoes rearrangement.
And those progenitor cells become CD4 positive helper cells or they can graduate and become CD8 positive cytotoxic T cells.
And all of this development normally occurs in the thymus.
Now it's important to remember that the T cell receptor complex is really the way by which T cells can see antigen.
That's their, that's the specific way by which they detect antigen.
And we say T cell receptor complex because the T cell receptor complex actually contains both the T cell receptor along with CD3.
So CD3 is also part of that complex.
And it's this complex that recognizes antigen.
Remember that it's restricted to that antigen that's presented on MHC.
T cell receptors are only able to see antigen for the most part.
Again, general principle, T cell receptors are only able to see antigen that is presented on MHC.
In particular, you need to be aware of, and I'm sure, I'm hopeful at this point, you are aware of, that CD4 positive T cells, they recognize MHC class 2.
CD8 positive T cells, they recognize antigen presented on MHC class 1.
And there's a famous mnemonic where, you know, these are CD4, and this is MHC class 2, so 2 times 4 is 8.
And these are CD8s, and this is MHC class 1, and so 8 times 1 is also 8.
And so you always want it for, you always want to get to the number 8.
Regardless, you do need to know that CD4 positive T cells recognize MHC class 2,
and CD8 positive T cells, they recognize MHC class 1, or antigens bound to MHC class 1.
Now, activation of T cells actually requires binding of antigen and the MHC complex.
So, again, I told you that T cells will only recognize antigen that is bound to the MHC complex.
However, the T cell, once it recognizes the antigen bound to the MHC complex, that's not sufficient enough for the T cell to be activated.
It is going to require an additional second signal before the T cell will actually be allowed to become activated and then produce its function.
And so let's talk about how T cells get activated, because that is important for examinations.
CD4 positive T cell activation occurs via extracellular antigen.
Now, let's go back.
You know that CD4 positive T cells, they recognize MHC class 2.
And MHC class 2 is predominantly present on antigen-presenting cells.
What do antigen-presenting cells do?
They basically take antigen from the outside world, they phagocytose it, they process it, and then they express it on MHC class 2.
So an example would be macrophages or dendritic cells.
These are cells that have the ability to phagocytose extracellular antigen, present it on MHC class 2, and show it to the CD4 positive T cell.
Now, the second signal, remember that the CD4 positive T cell requires a second signal.
Basically, all T cell activation requires a second signal.
And so the second signal is going to be B7, which is present on the antigen-presenting cell, will bind CD28 on the CD4 positive T cell.
And that provides a second activation signal.
And if you're having trouble remembering that, then you can remember that 28 divided by 7 is 4.
So that provides a second activation signal.
Now, once CD84 positive T cells are activated, then they will secrete cytokines.
And these cytokines help inflammation.
And that's why they're called CD4 positive helper T cells, because they help inflammation.
And interestingly, the CD4 positive T cells will be divided into two subsets.
And the two subsets will actually help the two types of inflammation that occur in chronic inflammation.
Why don't I take you one slide back and just go over this briefly.
So the CD4 positive T cell, right, the CD4 positive T cell's job is to help.
And it's going to help two types of inflammation.
It can help B cells, right, or it can help CD8 positive T cells.
And these are the two types of inflammatory responses.
And these are the two things that helper T cells will help.
And so they're actually helper T cells are divided into two subsets.
The first is the Th1 subset.
And the Th1 subset helps the CD8 positive T cells.
Now, it helps the CD8 positive T cells by generating IL-2, which is a T cell growth factor,
and a CD8 positive T cell activator.
And it also helps the CD8 positive T cells by activating macrophages via interferon gamma.
So these are the key products of the Th1 subset.
And you do have to be familiar with these products for examinations.
And you do need to know what they actually do as well.
The Th2 subset, what it does, it helps the B cells.
And what it helps the B cells by producing IL-4 and IL-5.
These are really the two big molecules that you need to be familiar with.
The IL-4 causes class switching to IgG and IgE.
And the IL-5 helps to bring in eosinophils, causes maturation of B cells to plasma cells,
and allows for class switching to IgA.
Now, another product of the Th2 subset is to produce IL-10.
And IL-10 inhibits the Th1 phenotype.
We've already also talked about IL-10 in the context of, do you recall where we talked about IL-10?
When I talked to you about macrophages and how the macrophages come in
and they manage the last step of acute inflammation,
and I said that one possibility was resolution of the inflammatory response.
And so, remember that the macrophages produced IL-10 there to sort of shut down the inflammatory response.
So, anyway, this is the key function of the Th2 subset of helper T cells.
Now, that's the way by which CD4 positive T cells are activated.
CD8 positive T cells are going to be activated by the following.
Well, first of all, CD8 positive T cells, they recognize MHC class 1.
And we need to go back and review from basic immunology, how does antigen get loaded on MHC class 1?
Well, it's intracellular antigen.
Remember that basically a sampling of the protein being produced within the cell gets loaded on MHC class 1
and allows the CD8 positive T cells to determine whether there is a foreign protein being produced within the cell.
And so, MHC class 1 predominantly expresses intracellular antigen.
The CD8 positive T cell recognizes MHC class 1, and that really is the first signal.
But recall that T cells require an additional signal.
And so, the second signal is IL-2 from the CD4 positive T cell.
Remember that the CD4 positive helper 1 subtype, the Th1 subtype,
it helps CD8 positive T cells, as I've already explained.
And the IL-2 from the helper T cell allows for the second signal,
allowing the CD8 positive T cells to become activated.
Once the CD8 positive T cells are activated for killing,
the way by which they kill the cells is that they actually,
the way by which they kill the antigen is to actually kill the cell in which the antigen is present.
And we've already talked about that when we talked about apoptosis.
So, how do CD8 positive T cells kill their target?
They secrete perforins, and that perforates a hole in the cytoplasm of the target.
Granzyme enters, and once granzyme enters, it induces apoptosis of the target cell.
That's the way by which CD8 positive T cells kill.
Now, do you remember, I'm going to try to jog your memory here
and remind you of a high yield that shows up on examinations.
What is the key enzyme that mediates apoptosis that the,
in this particular case, that granzyme would activate?
Caspase.
So, remember that caspases are the key mediators of apoptosis.
That's high yield, okay?
Now, that's one way by which the CD8 positive T cells will kill.
Another way by which the CD8 positive T cells kill
is that they actually express something called Fas ligand.
Now, Fas ligand has the ability to bind Fas on the target cell,
and Fas is an activator of apoptosis.
And if you recall, again, sort of, let's do a little circular review.
Remember that there are three ways by which we activate the caspases.
Do you remember those?
So, one way by which we activate the caspases was the intrinsic mitochondrial pathway,
and that was really driven by cytochrome C leaking out from the mitochondria
and activating the caspases.
Another way that we activate the caspases was via extrinsic receptor pathway,
and an example of that was Fas-Fas ligand.
Another example of that was TNF binding the cells.
And then a third way by which we activate apoptosis
is the CD8 positive T cell dumping granzyme,
which then activates the caspases, which activates apoptosis.
So, again, this is the mechanism by which CD8 positive T cells kill their target.
Okay, B lymphocytes.
Let's go to B lymphocytes very briefly.
B lymphocytes are produced as immature B cells in the bone marrow,
and they undergo Ig rearrangement to become naive B cells.
So, basically, the naive B cells, they are sort of the baby B cells,
and they express on their surface IgM and IgD.
So, the very initial B cell does express IgM and IgD on its surface.
Now, how do B cells get activated?
There's two ways.
The first way by which B cells get activated is antigen binds the IgM or IgD.
So, for example, this is a B cell.
It's got a surface receptor.
Let's say that this surface receptor is actually IgM.
All right?
An antigen comes.
It binds the surface IgM.
That sends a signal to the B cell,
and this B cell will then become a plasma cell,
and it will become an IgM-secreting plasma cell.
So, that's one way by which B cells can become activated.
Another way by which B cells can become activated is that the B cell can present antigen to the CD4-positive T cell by MHC class 2.
The CD4-positive T cell will then interact with the B cell.
The second signal, that's the first signal.
The second signal for the helper T cell will be that CD40 on the B cell will bind CD40 ligand on the helper T cell,
and that then activates the B cell.
All right?
So, this is actually very high yield, and you'll see why when we come into immune deficiency.
But there are two ways by which the B cell can be activated.
The first would be for antigen to bind surface IgM,
which then causes the B cell to become a plasma cell and secrete IgM.
And the second would be for the B cell to consume the antigen, to present the antigen on MHC class 2,
for the CD4-positive T cell to then recognize it,
and then the B cell would give a second signal, which is CD40, to the helper T cell,
and that CD40 second signal would provide the activation signal that would then activate the T cell.
And, of course, activation of the helper T cell is going to result in what?
It's going to result in production of IL-4 and IL-5,
and that's going to allow for B cells to isotype switch, undergo hypermutation, and mature to plasma cells,
so that these B cells will now be able to secrete IgE, IgG, IgA,
because, remember, the B cell starts as secreting IgM or IgD.
But in order to go beyond IgM or IgD to be able to secrete IgG, IgE, and IgA,
you're actually going to need to undergo this type of reaction from the helper T cell.
Is that clear?
And, again, I'm going to highlight this a little bit later when we talk about immune deficiency.
Okay, next sort of sub-discussion, and that is granulomatous inflammation.
Now, when you talk about chronic inflammation, well, why don't we take a step back?
When you talk about inflammation, inflammation is divided into acute and chronic.
And then when you talk about chronic inflammation,
chronic inflammation is subdivided into granulomatous and non-granulomatous.
So granulomatous inflammation is a subtype of chronic inflammation.
Now, the characteristic of granulomatous inflammation is a granuloma, hence the name,
and the key cell, this is very important,
the key cell that defines a granuloma is an epithelioid histiocyte.
All right, this is a very common exam question.
They can ask, or examiners can ask, what is the key characteristic,
what is the defining characteristic of a granuloma?
And the answer is epithelioid histiocyte.
What is an epithelioid histiocyte?
Now, macrophages, normally they have a foamy cytoplasm.
It's a relatively clear cytoplasm.
However, when macrophages get activated, they can actually become activated
so that they develop abundant pink cytoplasm, and those are called epithelioid histiocytes.
And the aggregate of epithelioid histiocytes is called granuloma.
So when you have aggregation of epithelioid histiocytes, that's called a granuloma.
Now, there are some additional features of a granuloma.
They're not necessary for a granuloma, but they can also, or they're usually also seen with a granuloma.
For example, giant cells are usually also seen with a granuloma.
And a rim of lymphocytes are also usually seen with granuloma.
But let me make it very clear.
The defining feature of a granuloma is an epithelioid histiocyte, high yield.
Please keep that in the back of your mind.
All right, one last point, and that is that granulomas can be divided into non-caseating and caseating subtypes.
So let's kind of touch on this very briefly.
Now, the reason it's important to recognize or understand granulomatous inflammation
is because granulomatous inflammation actually carries a very particular differential diagnosis.
There are a set or a limited number of things that actually give you granulomatous inflammation.
And so by knowing that there's granulomatous inflammation, you get a very distinct differential
for what is actually driving the inflammatory process in that particular patient.
So the first type of granuloma, as I've mentioned, is a non-caseating granuloma.
And it's defined by the fact that it lacks central necrosis.
And I'll show you a picture in a minute.
But basically, these types of granulomas, they arise in reaction to foreign material.
So, for example, if a patient has a history of breast cancer, the breast is removed,
and the patient gets implants in the breast as part of a reconstruction,
it's possible that those implants could leak, and they would release foreign material into the lymphatics,
which would then go into the axillary lymph node and produce enlarged lymph nodes within the axilla.
So that would be an example of reaction to foreign material.
And it's important because if a patient has a history of breast cancer and has implants,
and let's say that the patient comes in and says that she feels lymph nodes within her axilla,
you know, there's a differential diagnosis there.
The possibility is that the patient has recurrence of her breast cancer or maybe spread of her breast cancer,
and it's now involving the axilla.
Or it's also possible that there's a reaction to foreign material, i.e. the foreign material from the implant,
which is then creating granuloma.
So if a biopsy was performed and there was cancer, that would be very different than a biopsy being performed to the lymph nodes
and showing non-caseating granulomas.
So that's one example.
Another example would be sarcoidosis.
Sarcoidosis is a disease that we'll talk about when we do respiratory.
However, its characteristic hallmark is the production of non-caseating granulomas in multiple tissues throughout the body,
in particular the lung.
But again, we'll touch on that when we do the respiratory lecture.
Beryllium can also cause the formation of non-caseating granulomas predominantly within the lung,
but in other tissues as well.
And beryllium and sarcoidosis are sort of on the same,
sort of can create a very similar clinical picture, especially on exams.
So I will talk about beryllium and sarcoidosis in much more detail when we do the lung section,
but it is a classic exam type question that we'll discuss when we get there.
Crohn's disease is classically associated with non-caseating granulomas.
If I asked you what's the histologic hallmark of Crohn's disease,
you would tell me non-caseating granulomas.
If I asked you what's the histologic hallmark of ulcerative colitis,
which is sort of the sister to Crohn's disease, what would the answer be?
The answer would be crypt abscesses.
And crypt abscesses basically mean that if you look at the colon,
you know that the colon is made up of a bunch of crypts that sort of line up as a test tube,
and in the bottom of these crypts you get neutrophils.
And so those are called crypt abscesses, or crypt abscess,
and that is the histologic hallmark of ulcerative colitis,
whereas the histologic hallmark of Crohn's disease is a non-caseating granuloma.
And again, you have to know the histologic hallmark.
It's very important to be aware of.
And then finally, another example, and again, this is a limited list.
You could keep going, but another example would be cat scratch disease.
And cat scratch disease, the classic description of those granulomas
are non-caseating granulomas, and what's very important is usually it's in the neck,
and it gives you a stellate-shaped granuloma.
And that's a very classic thing to be aware of for examinations,
that cat scratch disease gives you a stellate-shaped granuloma.
All right, so let's keep moving.
This is a picture of a non-caseating granuloma.
And what I mean by, first of all, why is it a granuloma?
Because you've got this aggregate here of these histiocytes with pink cytoplasm,
and these are epithelioid histiocytes, so that makes it a granuloma.
You can see that there are a lot of lymphocytes associated with it,
and so that's an additional bonus.
And then you can see the production of these giant cells,
where you have a cell with a lot of cytoplasm and multiple nuclei.
That's a giant cell.
It's a multinucleated cell with abundant cytoplasm.
And so here is sort of the classic granuloma.
Now you'll notice that when you look at this granuloma,
each of the histiocytes has their nucleus present.
So this is non-caseating.
It is not necrotic, okay?
And so that is the histologic hallmark of a non-caseating granuloma.
Now, the opposite of that would be a caseating granuloma.
Let me do this histology first and then walk you through the prior slide.
But this is an example also of a granuloma.
Here, what we're seeing is the edge here.
Actually, you can more appropriately make out the epithelioid histiocytes.
But what I want to highlight within this aggregate here is that in the center, this is all dead.
We don't really see the nuclei.
We see sort of this pink debris and this blue debris.
We're not really able to make out the cells as well.
Let's compare again.
So this is A.
Erase the markings.
This is A, which was a non-caseating granuloma.
And you can see this is B.
And in B, you can see that there is necrosis and cell death.
And so that's what makes up the caseating granuloma.
Now, what's the key differential diagnosis for the caseating granuloma?
Well, the caseating granuloma is the key differential is TB and fungus.
All right?
So that whenever you have a caseating granuloma, sort of number one and number two on your list are going to be TB and fungus.
And so one thing that we can do as pathologists, and you do have to be familiar with this, is we can do something called an AFB stain.
And the AFB stain allows us to look for TB.
And we can also do something called a silver stain, also known as a GMS stain.
And the GMS stain allows us to look for fungus.
And so whenever we have a caseating granuloma, we want to make sure that the AFB stain is negative and the GMS stain is done as well to ensure that there is no TB and that there is no fungus.
Okay.
Now, the next important thing to be aware of are the steps that are involved in granuloma formation.
So how are granulomas formed?
Very high yield for examinations.
I'm going to tell you a couple things that could easily show up on an exam.
First of all, the formation of a granuloma is an interaction between macrophages and CD4 positive Th1 helper T cells.
Okay.
That's 0.1.
That's the first thing I would say you have to know.
Now, what happens is the macrophages find the antigen.
They express it in MHC class 2 because they are antigen-presenting cells.
And the helper T cells, they recognize that.
When they recognize, when that interaction occurs, the macrophages then secrete IL-12.
That's high yield, IL-12.
IL-12 induces the CD4 positive T cells into the Th1 subtype.
The Th1 subtype cells then secrete interferon gamma, and that's what converts the macrophages to epithelioid histiocytes.
Now, I realize there's a lot of words on this slide, but I want to really make it simple.
Step 1, the macrophages find an antigen presented via MHC class 2 to the helper T cells.
The helper T cells, okay, bind the antigen.
Once that first binding occurs, the macrophages sort of then dump IL-12 and the CD4 positive Th, which then converts the CD4 positive cells to a Th1 subtype.
The Th1 helper cells then secrete interferon gamma, which then converts the macrophages to epithelioid histiocytes.
So, you have to know IL-12 from the macrophages, and you have to know interferon gamma from the Th1 helper T cells.
So, that should be clear.
Now, I want to make this very clear because this is the way the examiners go after it.
This step, the step of IL-12 and interferon gamma, it occurs in both caseating and non-caseating granulomas.
So, both caseating granulomas and non-caseating granulomas are both formed in this particular way.
That really closes off our discussion of chronic inflammation, and we're going to take a little break here and then come back and discuss primary immunodeficiency.
Thank you.